<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Allegations of the Turky Company and others against the East-India-Company, relating to the management of that trade presented to the Right Honourable the Lords of His Majesties most Honourable Privy Council, the 17th of August, 1681 : together with the answer of the said East-India-Company thereunto, delivered in writing the 22th instant according to Their Lordships order, upon which a hearing was had ... the 24th of the said month.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8675</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11648583</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11648583</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47985</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26676)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47985)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 4:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Allegations of the Turky Company and others against the East-India-Company, relating to the management of that trade presented to the Right Honourable the Lords of His Majesties most Honourable Privy Council, the 17th of August, 1681 : together with the answer of the said East-India-Company thereunto, delivered in writing the 22th instant according to Their Lordships order, upon which a hearing was had ... the 24th of the said month.</title>
                  <author>East India Company.</author>
                  <author>Company of Merchants of England Trading to the Levant.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Wing's title reads "Turkey".</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47985:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47985:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE ALLEGATIONS OF THE <hi>Turky Company and Others</hi> AGAINST THE Eaſt-India-Company, Relating to the Management of that Trade: Preſented to the Right Honourable the Lords of His Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy Council, the 17th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1681.</head>
            <head type="sub">Together with the Anſwer of the ſaid <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> thereunto, Delivered in Writing the 22th. inſtant according to their Lordſhips Order, Upon which a Hearing was had before their Lordſhips the 24. of the ſaid Month.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The preſent State of Trade between the Company of Merchants Trading in the Dominions of the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> and the Company of Merchants Trading into the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as it now ſtands in reference to the Common benefit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> THE Company of Merchants Trading into the Dominions of the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> have for near one hundred years paſt conſtantly Exported great quantities of the Woollen Manufactures, and other Commodities of the Growth of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Turkey,</hi> to the great Inriching of this Nation; And do now more eſpecially carry out thither or the like Native Commodities yearly to the value of about Five Hundred Thouſand Pounds <hi>ſterling;</hi> in return of which, the Goods Imported are, <hi>Raw ſilks, Gaules, Grograms, Yarn,</hi> and <hi>Cotton,</hi> &amp;c. All which as well thoſe Imported as Exported, are Manufactured in <hi>England,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Bread to the induſtrious poor of this Nation.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47985:2"/>
               <p n="1">I. The <hi>Eaſt-India Company,</hi> on the other ſide, Export from <hi>England</hi> immenſe quantities of Gold and Silver, with an inconſiderable quantity of <hi>Cloth,</hi> which ſerves them only to give a colour of ſome benefit to the Nation, or rather to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper and moderate the Complaint which otherwiſe would be made againſt them. In return of which their chiefeſt Commodities are <hi>Callicoes, Pepper, wrought Silks,</hi> and a deceitful ſort of <hi>Raw ſilk, Callicoes,</hi> and <hi>wrought ſilks</hi> Manufactured in <hi>India,</hi> being an evident dammage to the Poor of this Nation, and the latter of <hi>Raw ſilks</hi> an infallible deſtruction to the <hi>Turkey</hi> Trade, for in regard that <hi>Turkey</hi> doth not yeild a ſufficient quantity of Commodities, to return for one fourth part of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures Exported thither, the remaining Ballance which is three quarters of Our Trade, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z'd, by <hi>Raw ſilks,</hi> which if ſupplied by that of a baſer and worſe ſort out of <hi>India,</hi> the moſt conſiderable part of the <hi>Turkey</hi> Importations, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Cloth Trade of <hi>England</hi> muſt fail: And then it will appear how diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent it is, in reference to the welfare of His Majeſties People, to have Silks pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with the Bullion, rather than with the Manufactory of this Nation.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The Conſtitution of the <hi>Turkey Company</hi> being a regulated Company, and not driven by a Joint-ſtock, is open and comprehenſive, admitting any that are bred Merchants, ſuch as are Sons and Apprentices to Freemen, challenge their Freedom by ſervice of ſeven years, ſuch as are, and have been neither, yet upon payment of Twenty Five pound, if under Twenty ſeven years of Age, or if above, upon payment of Fifty pounds, are freely admitted into all the Privileges of the <hi>Turkey Company,</hi> and each to Adventure and Trade for as much as he is able, by which open way of dealing, this Company is increaſed, from ſixty or ſeventy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who Forty years paſt wholly drove the Trade, to at leaſt Five Hundred Traders, who do Annually breed at leaſt One Hundred Noble-mens and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Sons in the <hi>Turkey</hi> Trade, and dayly new admiſſions are made, by which it may plainly appear how open his Majeſties Charter lies, and how diffuſive his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Goodneſs therein is, without any reſtraint or appropriation to particular Perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company on the other ſide, manage their Trade by a Joint Stock, confined to the narrow compaſs of ſome few perſons, excluſive to all others, under the penalty of Mulcts, Fines, Seizures, and other extraordinary proceedings. And upon an exact inquiry it will be found, that this Stock is ſo ingroſſed, that about ten or twelve men have the abſolute management of the whole Trade (there being one who hath at leaſt Eighty Votes) and about forty men do not only di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Major part of the gains, but not content therewith, do alſo indirectly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to themſelves a greater profit in a ſeparate Trade, as in <hi>Musk, Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeſe,</hi> &amp;c. and till of late in <hi>Diamonds</hi> alſo: So that here is the certain effect of a Monopoly to enrich ſome few, and empoveriſh many— Moreover the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company by their Conſtitution are incapable of breeding up any perſons under the Notion of an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Merchant: For they can neither give them Freedom, nor other Priviledge to Trade, as the <hi>Turkey</hi> Company doth, unleſs they become pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers of part of the Joynt-ſtock, as any one may do who is Maſter of Money.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The Stock of the <hi>Turkey</hi> Company is as large as the Eſtates of the many Traders are, and is really greater than the Trade will bear under the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and Checks given to it by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, and if any loſs or dammages befalls this Stock, every particular Member bears the loſs of his own Adventure, with no dammage to the Publick.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47985:2"/>
               <p n="3">III. The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, on the other ſide, have a fixed Joint-ſtock of about three Hundred and ſeventy Thouſand pounds: And becauſe they find it more to their advantage to Trade with Money at Intereſt, than to enlarge their own Stock, they have borrowed at leaſt ſix hundred and fifty thouſand pounds on their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Seal, at the inconſiderable Intereſt of three or four <hi>per Cent.</hi> whereby they Trade with the Treaſure of the Nation, dividing to themſelves what ſums they pleaſe, not only out of the profit, but alſo out of the principal, as by a late exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the laſt year may appear, when they divided in One year two hundred and ſixty Thouſand pounds, though at the ſame time they owed above ſix hundred Thouſand pounds at Intereſt. But in caſe any misfortune happens to what danger will all the Lenders of ſo great a part of the Treaſure of the Nation be expoſed, when the flouriſhing Eſtates of particular men cannot be made liable to thoſe Debts, contracted under the Common Seal, which gave Life and Being to them, and from whence they aroſe; So that the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> againſt the Rules of Juſtice and Reaſon, ſecurely enjoy the benefit of the Trade, and yet have little ſhare in the hazard and loſs thereof.</p>
               <p>Upon conſideration of the whole matter, it is humbly hoped, that for relief of the now languiſhing, though moſt uſeful and neceſſary <hi>Turkey</hi> Trade; His <hi>Majeſty</hi> will be graciouſly pleaſed, to permit to the <hi>Turkey Company,</hi> the exerciſe of Trade in the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and all other the Dominions of the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> according to the large extent of their Charter, and acceſs thereunto, by the moſt convenient paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; and to forbid the <hi>Eaſt-India Company,</hi> to import <hi>Raw,</hi> or <hi>wrought Silks,</hi> into <hi>England.</hi> And if this doth not ſeem a reaſonable expedient, that then His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> would be pleaſed to allot and limit a time to the <hi>Eaſt-India Company,</hi> to put an end to this preſent Joint-ſtock, (as by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Charter is provided) and that Books be laid open for New ſubſcriptions, whereby a larger Joint-ſtock may be raiſed, without Loans, or Money at Intereſt, ſo that the <hi>Turkey Company</hi> who by the incroachment of the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> upon them, have loſt or muſt looſe the greateſt part of their Trade, may have ſome reparation by partaking of theirs. And that by Proviſo in the New Charter, they may be defended by a Prohibition of <hi>Raw,</hi> and <hi>wrought Silks</hi> out of <hi>India,</hi> which is not only a certain Ruine to the <hi>Turkey</hi> Trade, but conſequently a prejudice to the whole Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47985:3"/>
               <head>Reaſons againſt the Management of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, as now driven under the preſent Joint-Stock.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE continuance of the Stock which has now laſted 24 Years, is againſt the <hi>Eaſt-India Companies</hi> firſt propoſal in their Preamble; Whereby it was agreed, That at ſeven Years end the Stock ſhould be balanced and divided, and a new Subſcription made; and that any Perſons at the ſaid ſeven Years end, might go out or come in, upon a valuation then to be made known; tho' it be now above 3 times ſeven Years, and no ſuch thing done. 'Tis true the Company declared about that time, that ſuch as would come in, or go out, ſhould do it by ſuch a time then prefixt, but no valuation being made Publique before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, the Goers out, or Comers in, might be wrong'd unavoidably, as well by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Valuation upon the One, as ſinking it upon the Other, as they pleaſed; and this was the Reaſon that then no one Perſon either went out or came in, which miſchief by a fixt previous Valuation, as it was firſt propoſed, would have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided. And this Preamble, after it had ſerved for a ſpecious pretence to draw in ſubſcribers, was laid aſide and became uſeleſs; ſo that the Fiſh being taken, the Net was flung away.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company have ſent over into <hi>India, Throwſters, Weavers,</hi> and <hi>Dyers,</hi> and actually ſet up there a Manufacture of Silk, which not only by inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Indians</hi> in making theſe Manufactures, but by Importing them ready made, and Died, into <hi>England,</hi> is an unſpeakable impoveriſhment of the working People of this Kingdom, who would otherwiſe be imployed therein, and to the Ruine of many thouſands of Families here.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It being above 24 Years ſince the Stock was firſt underwritten, though many of the firſt Subſcribers muſt needs fall off, yet there is no liberty for young Merchants to come in on a New Subſcription. And there are Thouſands of Able and Active Merchants bred up ſince their Stock begun, which are excluded ſo Rich and Great a Trade, meerly becauſe they were not born ſooner, or Bred up at that time; and nothing can be more Material, and Rational, than to plant New ones in the place of Old, That ſo the Spirit of Trade, like that of the Blood, may be kept in a conſtant Circulation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That ſo long Continuance of the Stock, is alſo the Reaſon, that the whole Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof is fall'n into the hands of 10 or 12 Men, and in all likelihood in a few years may come into the hands of 3 or 4, in regard thoſe that have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Stock ſtill buy more, and one of them at preſent hath at leaſt 80 Votes, by which plurality of Voices in one Man, not only the whole Trade of ſo many vaſt and rich Countries is Govern'd, but the Profit thereof ſhared by a very few Perſons.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company Export great quantities of <hi>Bullion,</hi> with a ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Cloth, which they do only for a colour to gild over the Dammage of their Exporting Money, or elſe to Moderate the Complaint would be otherwiſe made againſt them, and as they are little or no benefit to the Nation, by their Exporting any Manufacture thereof, ſo they import ſcarce any thing but what is ready Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factured, as <hi>Callicoes,</hi> and <hi>wrought ſilks;</hi> excepting lately a deceitful ſort of fuzzy ſlight Silk, a pound whereof being Died, weighs at leaſt 4 ounces more than it did before the Dying, whereas the beſt Silk weighs rather one ounce or two leſs after Dying. And hence it might be Conſidered, how different it is in Reference to the Welfare of <hi>England,</hi> to have forreign Importations purchaſed with the Bullion, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than with the Manufactory of our own Nation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Company being in all 550 Perſons, as they pretend, there is not above one fifth of them Merchants, and the Government of the Trade lies in the hands of thoſe few Merchants only, who by their skill in Trade, whereof the others are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47985:3"/>ignorant, ſet up a particular Intereſt, and drave a Trade for themſelves, ſeparate from the joint Stock, and appropriate the greateſt quantity of ſeveral of the beſt Commodities to themſelves, with Limitation and Reſtraints, to others of the ſame Company, whereby under a Pretence of a General Intereſt, a particular one is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, and promoted, and the private Intereſt of a few is managed diſtinctly, and apart from the publique joint-Stock; as for Example, <hi>Musk, Ambergreece,</hi> &amp;c. and till of late <hi>Diamonds</hi> were limited, and reſtrained to certain Perſons ſo and ſo qualified, ſeparate and diſtinct from the Accompt of the joint-Stock, by which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct Artifices it becomes neerly related to a Monopoly, to enrich a few, and to impoveriſh many. And the Government of the Company being in the hands of thoſe few, which are Merchants, and alwayes of the Committee; They have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantage of preferring their ſeparate, and private Trade, before the Publique joint-Stock, in regard the Companies Factors abroad, as well as the Committee men at home are managed wholly by thoſe few that have great Stocks, who by that means having ſo great a Plurality of Votes, can diſplace both the one and the other, when they pleaſe, and put in ſuch as ſhall prefer their private Intereſt, ſo that their Committee-Men, and Factors muſt be ſubſervient to the ſeparate Intereſt, for fear of their being turned out of their Imployment. And hence it comes to paſs, that many of the choiceſt and richeſt Goods, are ſent home, on the private accompt of Particular Men, which are ſeldom or never ſent home on Account of the Joint-Stock. The Particular and diſtinct Intereſt, being alwayes preferred before the General and Publique, which Corruptions would be prevented, if upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement of a New Stock, its duration were limited to a ſhort Time, and the Subſcriptions to a Certain ſum, not to be exceeded.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The preſent Stock, being not above three hundred and ſeventy eight Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds, would by a New ſubſcription in one or more Stocks, be enlarged to 2 or 3 Millions, and ſo the more Money is Negotiated, the more Merchants, and other people, would be ſet on work, the more Ships and Marriners employed, the Trade more Extenſive and National, the Commodities of thoſe parts made Cheaper, and more got to the Kingdom in general, beſides to his Majeſty in particular, by his Cuſtoms.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Compare the largeneſs and extent of Companies Priviledges from the Cape of <hi>Good Hope</hi> to the Streights of <hi>Magellan,</hi> which is near two third Parts of the Trading World, with the ſmallneſs of their Stock, and by ſuch Compariſon it muſt needs appear their Stock is far too little, for the Trade of ſo many vaſt and rich Countries. And 'tis evident in Fact, that no Trade at all is driven to many of them, as <hi>Perſia, Japan, Arrachan, Achein, St. Laurence, Sumatra, Pegu, Madagaſcar, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſambique, Sofala, Melinde, Borneo, Zeiloan,</hi> and many others, and yet while they Trade not thither themſelves, they violently keep out others who would Trade, for their Stock being ſo ſmall, they only manage ſuch Trades which yields very great and exceſſive Profit, and neglect others, which probably might Anſwer, though not ſo immenſe a Profit, yet a very good Advantage, and more proportionable, to the time and hazard, than any Trade in <hi>Europe;</hi> which Places if Traded to, would not only carry off a great quantity of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commodities, but would alſo by Trading there, from one Port to another vend a large proportion of <hi>Indian</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and the Profit and Bullion ariſing thereby, would in a great meaſure ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, if not totally prevent, the Exportation of Bullion out of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Another Evidence that their Stock is too little for their Trade, may be their borrowing ſix hundred thouſand Pounds at Intereſt, which beſides the unmerchant-like way of Trading, by preferring a Dead to a Quick Stock, and electing rather
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47985:4"/>to Trade with Money at Intereſt, than to inlarge their <hi>Stock</hi> by new ſubſcriptions, is alſo a Publique danger to the Nation; for while they borrow ſo great a part of the Treaſure of the Kingdom, at ſo low an Intereſt as 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> they enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the Common Hazard, and divide and ſhare what they pleaſe, not only out of the Profit but out of the Principal it ſelf, the laſt Year dividing two hundred and ſixty thouſand Pounds, when at the ſame time, they owed ſix hundred thouſand Pounds at Intereſt. So that the Lenders clearly venture the hazard of their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal to Sea, for 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> while the Company make 50 <hi>per Cent.</hi> of it, without any hazard at all. And if any loſs ſhould happen by Captures at Sea, Stormes or other Accidents, the Lenders of ſo great a Treaſure have only the Companies Common Seal to depend on, which in ſuch Caſe is no ſecurity at all, for no one Member is obliged to make ſatisfaction, as hath been evident by ſeveral late Examples of the like Nature.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47985:4"/>
            <head>THE Eaſt-India-Companys ANSWER.</head>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhips,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to your Lordſhips Order of the 17th. Inſtant, we do give the following Anſwer, to every thing we think Material, in the <hi>Turkey</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Papers, preſented to your Lordſhips.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, To the Firſt Particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We pray your Lordſhips, as to the Quantity and Value of Cloth and Bullion Exported by each Company, to give no more Credit to the <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants, than to our Selves, but that the Entry at his Majeſties Cuſtom-Houſe may be the Meaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt ſay, which we hope will not be denied by the <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants, that generally, the Cloth that we Export for the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> is finer and of more Value, each piece of Cloth, than what the <hi>Turkey Company</hi> do uſually Export.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we are rightly informed, the Medium of the number of Clothes Export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the <hi>Turkey Company</hi> this laſt Three Years, doth not exceed 19000 Clothes, or thereabouts <hi>per annum;</hi> a greater quantity than which, (in value at leaſt) the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> may probably Ship out this Year, if their Factory at <hi>Amoy</hi> in <hi>China,</hi> be not ſurprized by the <hi>Tartars;</hi> of which there was a doubtful Report in <hi>India,</hi> when the laſt Ships came from <hi>Bantam:</hi> And within ſeven Years, if the Company be not obſtructed, they may Export more Cloth yearly, than ever the <hi>Turkey Company</hi> did or can do; Altho' formerly, before the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> had any Entrance into the Trade of <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Japan,</hi> the <hi>Turkey</hi> Companies Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Cloth, did much exceed the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Companies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſay, and it will be found by the Entries at the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe,</hi> that the <hi>Turkey</hi> Company do ſend out yearly, beſides their Cloth, great quantities of pieces of Eight from <hi>England,</hi> for the Purchaſe of their <hi>Raw-ſilk</hi> in <hi>Turkey;</hi> as well as great quantities of the like Species of Bullion from <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> which otherwiſe would come for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, To the ſecond Particular, concerning the compariſon they make, between the Conſtitution of the <hi>Turkey</hi> Company, and the <hi>Eaſt-India Company;</hi> We ſay, there hath been ſo much Printed, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, in moſt of the <hi>European</hi> Languages, and ſo many Conſultations, and Debates, in the great Councils of <hi>Europe,</hi> concerning Joynt-Stocks for the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:47985:5"/>Trade, within theſe two or three laſt Ages; and in all of them, the Reſult hath been for a Joint-ſtock, that we think it would be impertinent to trouble your Lordſhips with any long diſcourſe concerning it; but briefly;</p>
            <p n="1">1. It cannot be denied, by any Reaſonable man, but that a Joint-ſtock is capable of a far greater extenſion as to the number of Traders, and largeneſs of Stock, than any Regulated <hi>Company</hi> whatſover, becauſe in a Joint-Stock, Noble-men, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Shop-keepers, Widows, and Orphans, all the Kings Subjects of any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or Degree, may be Traders, and imploy their Stocks; whereas in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated <hi>Company,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Turkey Company</hi> is, by their own ſhewing, none can be Traders, but ſuch as they call Legitimate, or bred Merchants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And which is a conſequence of the former Reaſon, if the Trade of <hi>India</hi> were laid open, the Adventurers for <hi>India</hi> would certainly prove leſs by three quarters, than now they are; for in ſuch caſe, thoſe that have the skill only, would run away with the whole Trade, as in Fact they did, when that Trade was open about five and twenty years paſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though ſome few men have great Adventures in the preſent <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Stock, the number of all the Adventurers is now above ſix hundred Perſons, very many new ones having come in of late.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the indulged Trade, which all Adventurers (by the preſent Rules of the <hi>Company</hi>) have liberty to Trade in; every Adventurer without exception hath as full liberty according to his proportion of Stock as the Governour, Deputy, or any of the Committees; The ſame being not to exceed one fifth part of his Stock. And we can't apprehend, how it can be pretended, that ſuch indulged Trade is any way detrimental to the Nation, although it may be ſome abatement of Gain to the United Stock; which therefore, the greateſt Adventurers in the Committee, have conſtantly endeavoured to ſubdue, and have done it gradually every year; <hi>per ſaltum</hi> it cannot be done; It being not the work of a Year, nor of an Age, or two, to build up an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade to perfection, though it may be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a day; if intereſſed or unthinking Perſons Counſel might be taken. This truth is moſt eminently viſible in the proceedings of the Court <hi>France</hi> in their <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, theſe laſt Fourteen Years; that King, in the Conſtitution of his <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> ſpared not for coſt to obtain the beſt advice in <hi>Europe:</hi> Gave immenſe Rewards to ſuch as contributed any intelligence material to the laying of his Foundation; and for the encouragement of the firſt Adventurers, gave the priviledge of the Nobleſſe to any Perſon that ſhould ſubſcribe a conſiderable ſumme: Advanced to the <hi>Company</hi> without Intereſt for Ten Years, the fifth part of the whole deſigned Stock: Lent them for two or three Years, twelve of his great Men of War: And hath very lately for the further encouragement of the ſaid <hi>French Eaſt-India Company,</hi> given them <hi>gratis</hi> for ever that vaſt ſumme which he firſt advanced to them without Intereſt. And yet we ſee that <hi>Company</hi> doth yet make very little of it. And leaſt the <hi>French</hi> inſtance aforeſaid, ſhould be ſeemingly obviated by ſaying, they were beaten by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and ſo their <hi>Company</hi> ſpoiled: We muſt beg your Lordſhips pardon for enlarging this digreſſion, ſo far, as to inform your Lordſhips, that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company formerly, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had a Stock of Fifteen hundred thouſand pounds, did advance in Profit but twelve and an half in fifteen Years, from 1617 to 1632. And alſo ſeveral other <hi>Engliſh Stocks,</hi> ſince that time, have not been ſucceſsful in their attempts. And this very preſent Stock, when the beſt experienced Perſons of that time had la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured ſeven Years in it, after their Foundation; the Stock was ſold for ſixty <hi>per Cent.</hi> of the Principal.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For the number of Eighty Vote, which as is alledged, ſome ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon has in the choice of the Committees; We ſay, we know of no one Adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer that hath ſixty Votes at this time; but moſt reaſonable it is as hath been ever
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47985:5"/>practiſed in this, and the <hi>Royal Company,</hi> and every joint-Stock, that each Adventurer ſhould Vote according to his Stock: And we cannot imagine why any Man read in Hiſtory and Trade, ſhould conceive it detrimental to the Nation for any Perſon to purchaſe any kind of Perſonal Eſtate, that he can honeſtly obtain; the rather, becauſe even in <hi>Holland</hi> it ſelf, it is thought no publique dammage for one Jew to have ſix times the Value in their <hi>East-India</hi> Stock, that ever any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man had in this. But if your Lordſhips will pleaſe to judge all things by their conſequence, We do (in all Humility) appeal to your Lordſhips, whether ſince this Complaint of ſome Men having ſo great Stocks, which is about eight or nine Years con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, there have not been more great Ships built for the Companies ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, than were in Thirty Years before? Whether there hath not been much more of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Woollen Manufacture Exported than was formerly? Whether the <hi>Dutch</hi> Stock, which was at 580 pound <hi>per cent.</hi> or thereabouts, when the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-India</hi> Stock was but at ſixty <hi>per cent.</hi> or little more, have not ſtood at a ſtay, or declin'd, while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have advanced, ſo as almoſt to equalize them in the value of their Stock, and had certainly been above them, by this time, had not they been interrupted, by the late Inter-Lopers, and groundleſs Complaints. Whether many kinds of Commodities, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly indulged, have not been yearly taken into the joint-ſtock? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Majeſties Cuſtomes from the <hi>East-India</hi> Trade, be not more than doubled in value? Whether there have not been very many more Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, Chargeable, and ſucceſsful Attempts, for the obtaining of Trade, in the North-Eaſtern parts of <hi>India,</hi> viz. <hi>Siam, Cochin-China, China,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan?</hi> which, for ought we know (if throughly obtained) might Vend as much <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufactures as this Kingdom is able to make: And whether the Intereſt of the Companies Debts, hath not been abated from ſix to three <hi>per cent.?</hi> If theſe be the Conſequences of great Adventures, which all For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, as well as all unbiaſſed <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, will acknowledge, we cannot apprehend the leaſt ſhadow of Reaſon why any Perſons ſhould ſuppoſe ſuch great Stocks to be detrimental to the Kingdom, or to the <hi>Company,</hi> the greater any Perſons Intereſt is, the greater will his Care, Vigilancy and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry be.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, As to the third Particular, touching the ſmallneſs of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Companies Trading Stock, and the greatneſs of their Debt, and the lowneſs of their Intereſt, which are all Confounded in the ſaid Paper; We muſt Crave your Lordſhips leave to ſeparate, for your Lordſhips more clear Satisfaction.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Stock now in Trade, which they ſay is 370000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> We muſt own, ſo it was 24 Years paſt, and in like manner the <hi>Dutch</hi> Stock about 50 or 60 Years paſt was 600000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> but we ſay in fact, that our Stock now in Trade (clear of all our Debts, beſides our ſhipping, which alſo for the moſt part do belong to and are owned by the Adventurers) is at leaſt 1700000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> God ſending in ſafety our three Coaſt Ships, and one <hi>Bantam</hi> Ship, which we daily expect, and our next years Stock from <hi>India,</hi> which if we would inſure, we could do it at 3 or 4 <hi>per cent.</hi> at moſt. And tho' we numbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your Lordſhips would not think it fit to be made Publique, at leaſt, to Perſons unconcerned; if your Lordſhips ſhall think there is any ſtreſs to be laid upon this particular of the <hi>Turkey Companies</hi> paper, we ſhall be ready at your Lordſhips Command to make the Truth of what we have here aſſerted appear, by a ſtated Account Verified in ſuch manner as ſhall be to your Lordſhips indubitable Satisfaction.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:47985:6"/>
            <p n="2">2. As to the Companies Debt at Intereſt, it is about 550000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> which the <hi>Company</hi> have never concealed, nor diſowned, nor ever yet denied any Creditor his Debt both Principal and Intereſt, when ever it was deſired, whether due or not: And notwithſtanding all the Printed Intimations that have been given to the Creditors, that their Money is in danger, and that they have nothing, but a piece of Paper and Wax for their Payment; And that the Company are, or may be ſharing and dividing the Stock among themſelves; Yet ſuch is the Companies Credit with the World (whatever the <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants think of them) that they cannot perſwade their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors to take in their Money, nor without Offending Perſons (whom they would oblige) refuſe ſometimes the receiving in of Freſh Money at Intereſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the rate of Intereſt, whether a higher or lower Intereſt be Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally Diſadvantagious or Beneficial, is an ancient Theam which hath been Learnedly and Judiciouſly bandied in all Ages, and in moſt part of the Civiliz'd World; and ſome of us have had the Honour to Argue that Point before your Lordſhips in the Noble Houſe of Peers, where your Lordſhips upon the Queſtion (as we remember) did reſolve, that the Abatement of Intereſt, would tend to the increaſe of Trade and advance the value of the Lands of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have now Anſwered to the three General Propoſitions in the <hi>Turkey</hi> Companies Paper; but their whole Paper (as it ſeems to us) is ſo blended with other things, and inconſiſtent with it ſelf, in ſome Parts, That we muſt Crave your Lordſhips leave to make 2 or 3 Reflections upon the whole, and ſeparate the Concern of Silks from other things wherewith it is Mixed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſeem to find fault with the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> becauſe they are too few Traders, and yet at the ſame time blame them, for having others than bred Merchants; whereas, if the Company had none but ſuch, their number of Traders muſt be fewer by about three Fourths.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tho' they complain of the Fewneſs of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Adventurers as aforeſaid, and that other Merchants cannot get in amongſt them; In another place of the ſame Paper, they ſay, that any man that is maſter of Money may become a Pmrchaſer, of part of the joint-ſtock, which is true, and it is as true, that without Money, it is as difficult for a man to get a ſhare in the <hi>Turkey,</hi> or any other Trades.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſay, the Company do reſtrain Trade, by Fines, Seizures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and at the ſame time blame them for indulging ſome things to the Adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, as <hi>Musk, Ambergreece,</hi> &amp;c which ſeems to be an incoherent Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for the Company would (if they could) appropriate the whole Trade to the Joint-ſtock, as the <hi>Dutch</hi> do: But ſeeing they are compelled (by the defect of Power and Force of Uſage and Cuſtom) to indulge ſome ſmall things, as <hi>Ambergreece, Bezars, Rubies, Nutmegs, Cloves,</hi> &amp;c. they cannot be juſt without giving that liberty equally, and univerſally to all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers; as well as to their Factors, and Servants, Commanders, Officers, and Seamen.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They complain of the Languiſhing Condition of the <hi>Turkey</hi> Trade, and the hinderance the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company cauſes, of the Woollen Manufactures Exportation to <hi>Turkey.</hi> Whereas in Fact it will be found, if the Cuſtom-houſe books be examined, that during the Management of this very Complaint (which hath been of about 10 years Continuance) the Exportation of Cloth to <hi>Turkey</hi> hath not declined but increaſed as yet it will; Notwithſtanding the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company ſhould Load all their Ships from <hi>India,</hi> with Raw, and wrought <hi>Silks.</hi> That inſtance mentioned, in the late Printed Treatiſe, of the loſs of returns of <hi>Sugar</hi> and <hi>Cinamon</hi> from <hi>Portugal,</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47985:6"/>taking of <hi>Ceilon,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> vaſt productions of <hi>Sugar</hi> from <hi>America,</hi> is pregnant and irrefragable to this Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In the conſideration of <hi>Silk,</hi> we ſhall with your Lordſhips leave, ſpeak diſtinctly to the ſeveral ſorts. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>Raw Silk.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>Wrought Silks plain.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>Wrought Silks flowered,</hi> or <hi>ſtriped.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, <hi>Wrought ſilks</hi> mixt with <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, As to <hi>Raw Silk,</hi> we ſay, it is ſo Eſſential a Commodity for the good of this Kingdom, that it may well hold Compariſon with our <hi>Wool,</hi> either <hi>Sheeps Wool,</hi> or <hi>Cotton Wool;</hi> which the wiſdom of the King and Parliament have ſo far indulged, as not to lay any kind of Cuſtom on either.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Since the <hi>Eaſt-India Companies</hi> Importation of great quantities thereof it is manifeſt, that the Manufacturers thereof have increaſed as much in number as from one to four.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For the Quality of what is brought from <hi>India,</hi> it is the ſame, and no otherwiſe than it is with all other Commodities upon the Face of the Earth, of various Qualities and Conditions, good, bad, and indifferent: The Buyers and the Uſers, are juſtly ſuppoſed to underſtand it better than we or the <hi>Turkey Merchants,</hi> and do ſet their own price upon it at our Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, as they find it anſwer in it's uſe and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to <hi>Wrought Silks</hi> plain from <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They are notoriouſly known to be the ſtrongeſt, and moſt durable, as well as the Cheapeſt that comes from any part of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are a Commodity generally exported from <hi>England,</hi> to other parts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For thoſe of them that are worn and uſed in <hi>England,</hi> they do only hinder the Importation of the like quantity from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and do not at all prejudice the <hi>Silk</hi> Manufacture of <hi>England,</hi> where they are very rarely or never made.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As to <hi>Wrought Silks Flowered,</hi> or <hi>Striped;</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We confeſs, they do a little impede the growth of the <hi>Silk</hi> Manufacture in <hi>England,</hi> but not to that degree in any meaſure as the <hi>Raw Silk,</hi> Imported from <hi>India</hi> doth advance it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſay, it would be unreaſonable to forbid the <hi>Eaſt-India-Companies</hi> Trading in them, except they were likewiſe forbidden to be Imported from any other part of the World. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. If they could be effectually forbidden from all parts; the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> would be glad to further, as much as in them lies, an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that purpoſe; and moſt earneſtly: If an invention could be found out to make ſuch a Law practicable, which is next to impoſſible, as we find by experience every day, in the <hi>French Silks,</hi> which are to be ſeen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt upon every <hi>Silk-mans ſtall,</hi> as well as on moſt peoples heads or backs, notwithſtanding the Act to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, For <hi>Wrought Silks</hi> mixt with <hi>Gold and Silver,</hi> they are indeed prejudicial to the Manufacturers of <hi>England;</hi> the Company do Import none of them. Notwithſtanding they are Imported from <hi>India,</hi> but it is (by the Companies leave) whether we will or no: For if we ſhould not permit them their Importation, they would come in as much as now they do by ſtealth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47985:7"/>in our own Ships, as well as by Interlopers: One whereof, <hi>Viz.</hi> The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous,</hi> Captain <hi>Criſp,</hi> hath vaſt quantities aboard at this time. If we ſhould Prohibit them ſo far as in us lies, there would be only this difference in the Caſe, thoſe kinds of <hi>Silks</hi> which now come openly, and pay the King Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, would come in by ſtealth from all Forreign parts, as well as <hi>India,</hi> and pay nothing to His <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding which, if a way can be found out by the Wiſdom of Parliament, to prevent the Importation, of ſuch kind of <hi>Wrought Silks,</hi> as aforeſaid from all parts of the World, as well as from <hi>India,</hi> none of His Majeſties Subjects ſhall more rejoyce at the paſſing of ſuch an Act, than the <hi>Eaſt-India Adventurers.</hi> But if we may preſume, by the way, to offer our own Humble and Sincere opinion, we do unfeignedly beleive; that no Law that the Wiſdom of men can invent, hath, or will ſo effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advance the Trade of the <hi>Silk</hi> Manufacturers in <hi>England</hi> as the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of great quantities of <hi>Raw Silk</hi> from <hi>India,</hi> ſo as to render that Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial <hi>(Silk)</hi> as cheap in <hi>England,</hi> as it is in any part of <hi>Europe</hi> where it grows.</p>
            <p>As to the Accuſation of ſending <hi>Throaſters, Weavers</hi> and <hi>Dyers,</hi> the <hi>East-India-Company</hi> ſay, the whole Accuſation is a miſtake, except only as to one or two <hi>Dyers,</hi> which they have uſually ſent to the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Bengala,</hi> and no other part in <hi>India,</hi> nor would they have ſent any thither, but that they did believe, and think, they are able to prove to your Lordſhips, that it was for the Nations as well as the Companies advantage, eſpecially as to the plain <hi>Black Silks,</hi> which they principally intended, and ſuch are generally a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Commodity here, very few or none being made in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Concluſion of the <hi>Turkey Companies</hi> Paper is in effect, that your Lordſhips ſhould adviſe His <hi>Majesty</hi> to Diſſolve this preſent <hi>Eaſt-India-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> as by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Charter is provided: that is (Your Lordſhips will pardon the expreſſion) to deſtroy that which is eſteemed by all Forreigners the Glory of the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> or otherwiſe to Mutilate it in ſuch manner, as was never practis'd by any <hi>European</hi> Nation: and thereby diſable the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> from ſerving his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> their Country or their ſelves: which is ſuch an Overture, that conſidering your Lordſhips great Wiſdom, we cannot but with the reſt of the World that are Strangers and Lookers-on, admire at the confidence of the Propoſers.</p>
            <p>The <hi>East-India Company</hi> have Stock enough: If they want more, they are able to encreaſe it at their pleaſure; if any other perſons deſire to come into the Trade, the <hi>Company</hi>'s Doors are alwayes open, they buy Stock at any time, cheaper than it's real and intrinſique value, the <hi>Company</hi> refuſes none of the Kings Subjects of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor can keep out any by their Charter, that will pay five pounds for their Admiſſion into their Freedom, which the preſent Adventurers paid themſelves.</p>
            <p>Purchaſe is the Natural way of coming into that Stock: Deſtruction will no more increaſe the number of their Adventurers than Caſtration or Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off a principal part of their Trade, as is propoſed by the <hi>Turkey Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:47985:7"/>
               <p>HAving Anſwered every thing we can Obſerve material in the firſt Paper, we meet with nothing new in the other Paper, called <hi>Reaſons againſt the management of the</hi> Eaſt-India-Company, <hi>as now driven under the preſent Joint-Stock.</hi> But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They ſay the Company have not valued their Stock at the end of every ſeven Years, according to the Preamble; Which is an Error in Fact. For whereas they alledge that the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> have not kept to their propoſals in their firſt Preamble, that does not Concern them. But therein they are likewiſe miſtaken, for that which they call a Preamble is but an Act of the General Court, although after ſubſcrib'd by all or moſt of the Adventurers, of which there are two only which have been made by this <hi>Company,</hi> and alterable at pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The firſt did provide, for a Valuation at the end of ſeven Years, which was accordingly made; and on a very long debate in a General Court, held at the <hi>Eaſt-India-Houſe,</hi> the 13th. of <hi>October,</hi> 1664. It was then determined, that every Adventurer ſhould within twenty dayes declare, whether he would go off upon the intended Valuation or not: And that it was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that thoſe, that did not declare in that time, continued their Stocks to all intents and purpoſes; which the ſaid General Court did think highly reaſonable, in regard that otherwiſe if the value of the Stock ſhould prove to come out above the ſelling rate (which was then but ſeventy <hi>per Cent.</hi>) All the Adventurers ſhould withdraw their Stocks, and conſequently diſſolve the <hi>Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The General Court was very numerous that time, and that Reaſon (among others) was ſo prevalent, that upon the queſtion there was but one Negative: After the valuation was made, which was one hundred thirty <hi>per Cent.</hi> Thirty days time was given for any Perſons to ſubſcribe a new, and they had full Liberty to peruſe the Valuation: But no new ſubſcribers did come in, notwithſtanding it appeared ſoon after, that the Stock was conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably undervalued and within a Year and a quarter following, there was fifty <hi>per Cent.</hi> divided.</p>
               <p>At another General Court Holden at the <hi>Eaſt-India-Houſe,</hi> the 16th. of <hi>March,</hi> 1664. The ſecond Preamble was made, and afterwards ſubſcribed by all the Adventurers, whereby the firſt Preamble was declared, determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and void: And in this Caſe to avoid the danger of diſſolving the ſtock aforementioned it was declared in the 4th. Article of the ſaid Preamble, that unleſs the generality at ſome General Court, ſhall otherwiſe direct, a valuation of all remains of Stock undivided, be once in ſeven years or ſooner, made by the Court of Committees between the firſt of <hi>May</hi> and the laſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> That thereby the Adventurers might ſee how the Stock ſtands, the better to ſell or buy, as to them ſhall be thought good; which hath been accordingly performed. Both which preambles, as they did only concern the Adventurers by whom they were made, and was never complained of to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47985:8"/>our Knowledge by any Adventurer: So with ſubmiſſion we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, they do no more concern our oppoſers than what we do in our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Families, we being under no obligation either by Charter or Promiſe, to do, or not to do any Act, at the pleaſure of Perſons unconcern'd in the Stock.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other Novel we obſerve in the ſaid Paper, is that the New Stock they propoſe, it's duration ſhould be limited to a ſhort time, and the ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to a certain ſum not to be exceeded; which are two ſuch abſurdities in the Polity of Trade, couched in two Lines, as were never heard of in any Trading Nation, in all the Debates and Foundations that ever were laid for the Eſtabliſhment of an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, or Trade in any of the Printed Books and Diſcourſes that have been in the <hi>European</hi> Nations, on that Subject. It being as Rational to make a Law that whoever plants an Orchard, ſhall plant it but for a ſhort time of Continuance, as to ſay that the Company, which cannot poſſibly arrive at its full growth in leſs than two or three Ages, ſhall be in its Conſtitution, Framed, and Limited to a ſhort continuance. And for the limited ſum they ſpeak of; that is no leſs detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to the Kingdom in General, by their own Maximes (ſo far as they do agree) as well as to the King's Revenue: For certainly the greater the Trade and Navigation, the more it is for Publique Advantage. Who the Traders be is a Perſonal Conſideration, and ſignifies nothing to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality.</p>
               <p>We have now anſwered all the Objections that we can find worth the troubling your Lordſhips with, in any of the aforeſaid Papers: And to right our ſelves we ſhould proceed, to enumerate to your Lordſhips the great and manifold Advantages which have accrued, and do accrue, to this Nation by the Envied Progreſs and Increaſe of the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-India</hi> Companies Trade: But thoſe are ſo many and ſo great, with Reſpect to his Majeſty and the Kingdoms Power, as well as profit that if we ſhould enter upon them they might ſwell this Paper into a Volume, and prove a Burthen to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, which therefore we ſhall forbear, praying your Lordſhips, for further ſatisfaction therein, to be referred to the printed Treatiſes that have been made publique on this Occaſion.</p>
               <p>But there is another thing which, with humble Submiſſion, we think it our duty to acquaint your Lordſhips with, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſtrange preſumption of the Inter-Lopers, theſe laſt 2 or 3 years, Of which two are already arrived, and one great Ship more is alſo expected home this year: And if an effectual Courſe cannot be taken to ſuppreſs that Inter-Loping Trade, it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to Frame a new or ſupport the old Company, who being at above one hundred Thouſand Pounds Annual Charge in Forts, Caſtle's, Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and otherwiſe, cannot be ſuppoſed to hold up in Trade, with thoſe that contribute nothing to that Charge; eſpecially conſidering that Inter-Lopers will ſave (as they call it) a great deal of the Cuſtom on fine goods of ſmall Bulk, whereas the Company upon Honour and Duty to his Majeſty, do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways pay the full Cuſtomes to a penny, and produce their true and original Invoices to the Kings Officers at any time.</p>
               <p>We had almoſt forgot the Allegation of the <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants, that their Members are 500, which if ſome Merchants of their own Company are not miſtaken, is an Error in their Muſter of at leaſt one half. And for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of Noblemen and Gentlemen's Sons as Apprentices, it is true, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47985:8"/>many ſuch they do breed up, and ſo do likewiſe the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company; with only two differences,
<list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants take 5 and 600 <abbr>
                           <hi>l</hi>
                        </abbr> with an Apprentice, the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, nothing.</item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Turkey</hi> Merchants Servants, ſuch as do well of them, come home with good indifferent Eſtates; thoſe that do well of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company's, with great ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>All that can be ſaid is; that an old Tree, that hath taken hold of the Ground, and drawn ſtrong Roots, may ſtand and abide more Shocks, Stormes, Blaſts, and Rubbs, than a young Tree that is newly Planted.</p>
               <p>We hope that by this our Submiſſive Reply to all that hath been ſaid againſt us, we ſhall have ſatisfied your Lordſhips of the Groundleſneſs of every Complaint. And if your Lordſhips ſhall ſo think fit, we humbly crave your Lordſhips Leave, for the Satisfaction of Perſons miſled, who otherwiſe may mean well, we may be permitted to Print the two Papers delivered us, with this our Anſwer.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>22 <hi>August,</hi> 1681.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>All which we Humbly Submit to your Lordſhips Grave Judgement and Conſiderations.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
